PHILIP GREENSPUN: There
is no pizza for me
because I'm going to
talk about Oshkosh.
So what is it?
It's end of July every year
at a big, a physically big,
but otherwise not very
busy airport in Wisconsin.
And about 10,000
airplanes come in.
People camp out.
People hang out, usually at
least 100,000 people a day.
There's a Boeing.
There's a C-17 cargo plane.
A lot of experimental-- it's
founded by the Experimental
Aircraft Association.
So there's a lot
of people who are
passionate about
home-building there.
You can see all the
airplanes parked.
There's 12,000 camping
sites, 40,000 campers.
There's 1,500
workshops and seminars
that you can take to learn.
Or you can just walk around and
talk to people, and hang out.
So I planned this trip
for me and my friend Ray.
He's a helicopter
pilot from Ireland.
And the idea was to
fly to Niagara Falls
and show him Niagara
Falls, and on the way
back go up to Mackinac Island.
They saw automobiles about
120 years ago and they said,
this is a terrible technology.
It'll ruin everything.
They banned cars.
The only powered air--
the only powered vehicle you can
legally have on Mackinac Island
is an aircraft.
They do have an airport.
Anyway, on the back, we were
going to go to Toronto as well.
So we had to get all this stuff
ready for international flying.
I had it all
carefully planned out
where we were going to
have 540 pounds of stuff,
which is right at the payload
of the airplane with full fuel.
But then Oxana,
who was just here--
she's an aerobatic pilot at
East Coast Aero Club-- she
said she wanted to come too.
So then we had to
add a fuel stop.
There's our merry
band of three people.
There's a whole bunch of
camping gear in the back
that you can't quite see.
Oshkosh becomes temporarily the
busiest airport in the world.
And you might say,
well, how can that be?
O'Hare has more flights.
But they are only--
Oshkosh is only open
about 10 hours a day
because they close
the airport at night.
And they close it also for
a few hours every afternoon
for an airshow.
This is somebody's iPad,
I think, a screen capture
of airplanes flying
in and around Oshkosh.
And these are only the
ones with the newest
ADS-B out transponders.
So it doesn't show, probably--
this is probably only 20%
of the total airplanes.
You have special arrival rules.
If you're not a
sissy, then you have
to fly in visually, circle
around until it's your turn.
And then they'll tell you you
can't use the whole runway.
You have to land on
one of these dots.
They'll say, land
on the green dot.
If you are a sissy, you file
IFR, get your IFR reservation
with this DOS grade
computer system,
confirm it with this DOS
grade computer system
that nobody else
wants to deal with,
and then you get the whole
runway, and you just land.
All right.
Here's a picture of the
multifunction display.
No, actually, I guess this
was in FlightAware later.
This shows that
we diverted a bit.
From Bedford, we ended up going
up to Watertown, New York,
so we didn't--
we could have-- legally,
we're instrument rated
and everything.
We could have flown
through these rain showers.
But it's always smarter just
to go around if you can.
OK.
So we flew over Niagara Falls.
We landed.
We had that whole
runway to ourself,
about 10,000-foot runway.
And it's actually
oriented east-west.
So we actually just--
essentially, we could have
done the same heading basically
from Hanscom Field all the
way to the end of the runway
and where we turned off.
You get there.
And there's just--
I don't know-- 30 P-51 Mustangs
right next to your tent.
There are people building this
One Week Wonder, an RV kit,
where you get to pull rivets.
Oxana is actually here.
And she can tell you
about her experience
helping to build that airplane.
There you see your B1 bomber.
I love the antiques.
Here's one from the late '20s,
a Lincoln-Page airplane that
has been recently
restored and flying.
There's that replica autogyro,
a beautiful Cessna 170.
That's an old Piper
Comanche there on the right.
There's not a whole lot
of helicopter action.
There's a little bit.
This is what's called a
Safari Helicopter Kit.
That's how you
know that you have
real confidence in your
mechanical abilities
if you build and then
fly your own helicopter.
Piper Cub.
This is a guy who stuck
a Pratt and Whitney--
I think it's a Pratt--
PT6 engine into a Polish Wilga,
a short field landing airplane.
He added fuel tanks.
It's such a fuel
hog now that he had
to add extra fuel
capacity in the struts
and flies all around the west,
going camping with his family.
All right.
And that's called a Travel Air.
There are a bunch of these.
So these are airplanes
from the '20s.
People were just using
them for transportation,
throwing a friend in the
back maybe and a tent
and going and camping
out at Oshkosh.
So I think that's pretty cool.
There are only five of these
Piaggio seaplanes, P136s,
that still exist out of 63 that
were built from 1948 to 1961.
I saw two of them parked next
to each other at Oshkosh.
That's what makes it
a unique experience.
Here's some kind of airplane
doing a simulated bombing run.
Meanwhile, a family is
there in their personal DC-3
camping out.
Here's our little plane and
the $99 tent from Costco.
It seemed like a great
idea at the time.
I think we have a slide on that.
OK.
This kind of summarizes it.
This is the unfortunate state
of general aviation now.
So we have the
innovation showcase.
And right in front of it, a
Piper Seminole, which I think
was certified in the 1970s
and certainly a derivative
of things going back a
lot farther than that.
There were some
interesting talks there,
some heavy hitters.
This guy Pat Anderson is a
professor at Embry-Riddle.
And he said actually
that we haven't really
seen anything in the
electric aircraft world
because in the
early days of jets,
they just took these piston
airframes and stuck a jet
engine in them.
And they didn't perform
that differently
from the piston fighters.
But then five years later,
they had the swept wings
and what we would recognize
as the modern fighter jet.
So it completely--
it was the jet
engine did completely
transform the aircraft,
but not immediately.
So he said, you're
seeing some of this now,
where people take a
little two-seat trainer
and they remove
the piston engine
and put an electric
motor with the propeller.
But that's not really--
what we're really
going to see are things
that are much more like drones.
There is an Uber.
There was a guy from Uber
that was very interesting.
Uber has aeronautical
engineers working for them,
designing aircraft, and then
releasing the designs for free,
hoping that people
will make them.
They're claiming that
they're going to--
I don't know.
They've got to pay somebody
off in the government
to make this happen.
2023 they say they're going to
be operating in Los Angeles.
Their idea is that
the world is going
to be so congested that
people will pay up happily
to hop over the congestion
in relatively short hops.
So Uber is putting a
lot of money into this.
They have some partners
like Airbus, Pipistrel,
the Slovenian company.
We'll see what happens.
So some round-the-world
pilots were there.
Actually, I don't know how many
you guys know this, but Matt
Guthmiller, who was an MIT--
between freshman
and sophomore years
became the youngest
person ever to fly around
the world in a
Beechcraft Bonanza.
I mean, he was in a
Beechcraft Bonanza
and he was the youngest person
to fly around the world.
But there's also-- at
Oshkosh, we met this guy
Dick Rutan who flew around
the world non-stop unrefueled
in a plane designed by
his brother Burt Rutan.
What else is Burt Rutan famous
for besides designing aircraft?
Does anybody know?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PHILIP GREENSPUN: What?
AUDIENCE: Wasn't he
on like a spacecraft?
PHILIP GREENSPUN:
Spacecraft, that's true.
But yeah, spacecraft and
aircraft, but what else?
AUDIENCE: Canard planes.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Canard
planes, those are airplanes.
Climate change denial.
Look it up.
He's got like a 100-page book
about the scientific fraud
of climate change.
But anyway, Dick Rutan.
And the other interesting thing
is before this nine-day flight,
he was engaged to be
married to Jeana Yeager
and supposedly what
I heard at Oshkosh
was that they have not spoken
since they landed in 1986.
So in nine days, there
can be quite a change
in a relationship apparently.
We met this pilot Shaesta Waiz.
I don't know if that's
the correct pronunciation.
She grew up in
California and learned
to fly relatively recently.
And she also flew a
Bonanza all the way
around the world over 145 days.
So that was interesting.
She actually said it gets a
little bit easier once you're
out over the ocean from
a weather point of view.
She said except for the
Intertropical Convergence
of the Equator,
most weather is kind
of a phenomenon of
being over land.
To me, the most impressive
round the world pilot,
though, was actually an
Italian guy that I met.
He was in a Cirrus SR22.
And he just flies to
Oshkosh every year.
He just loads up in Italy,
turns the key, and goes.
Every year, flies over
the Atlantic, and then
flies back to Italy
when it's over.
So I thought that is actually
the coolest thing, when
it's not even an adventure.
You're not going
to write about it.
You're not going to
build a web page.
You're not going to say
you're changing the world
or helping to achieve something.
You're not going
to set a record.
You're just using your
airplane for transportation.
You want to get to Oshkosh.
You have an airplane.
So why should the fact that
you're on a different continent
stop you from doing it?
A lot of people have stopped
doing home projects, home
repairs.
So Oshkosh, they actually
have people that teach kids
how to hammer, how to drill,
how to cut sheet metal.
There's a lot of great
workshops there for kids.
We were over by the Pioneer
Airport and the Museum.
Here is the museum.
They have a replica
Wright Flyer, a whole area
devoted to the Rutan designs.
I don't know how many--
I don't know how many of
you know the MIT spinoff
Terrafugia.
I guess-- I think it was
12-- at least 12 years ago,
they said they were going
to build a flying car.
So I took a picture of this
1949 Taylor Aerocar, which
is actually a
certificated flying car
and unfairly associated
with Terrafugia.
So this guy is kind of
an inspiration, I think--
Paul Poberezny, the founder
of the Experimental Aircraft
Association.
He flew the most expensive and
highest-performance aircraft
of the day.
He flew the P-51 Mustang,
the P-38 Lightning.
And then he came
home and said, well,
what's cool to do after flying a
12,000-pound-plus P-51 Mustang?
Why not just go to the
basement, get some plywood,
nail it together, and build a
really crummy plywood airplane?
And that's what he did.
So it just shows the joy.
You don't have to have a
high-performance, state
of the art airplane.
If you build it yourself
or you're goofing around,
you can have fun.
And he did.
And he was a better
pilot than [INAUDIBLE],,
I'm sure, in his P-51.
So that made me think maybe we
shouldn't be snobby about these
home-built airplanes, because
if it was good enough--
Poberezny had fun with it.
All right.
So here's some examples
of home-builts.
Up on the left there, there's
some kind of canard velocity.
These folks spent 15 years
building this helicopter.
And they had about 40
hours of flight time on it.
So to me, in a good
month at a flight school,
a Robinson helicopter might
fly 90 hours or 100 hours
in just a month.
So it's taken them 15 years
plus to get to where a flight
school would get in a month.
But that's kind
of not the point.
It's not about
efficiency apparently.
That's Rotorway kit, I bet.
And they modified it by sticking
in a little tiny turbine
engine.
This is another modification.
This is an old Rutan design
that became the Berkut
with a big piston engine.
This guy stuck a turbo
jet engine in it.
Here's the company--
yeah, 42,000--
I think that doesn't include
the engine, which is under 50.
You can build your own
little single-seat jet.
Cirrus was there.
Cirrus actually has been kind
of an industry-changing company.
It didn't seem that
way at the time,
because it's very
similar in performance
to Mooneys and
Pipers, and Cessnas.
But they really have
revolutionized the way
that families buy airplanes now.
And they've got
over 7,000 of them.
The parachute is, I
think, critical to getting
modern people to
accept this design.
And also the glass cockpit
does make life easier.
Although, everybody else
has caught up there.
Here's the Icon A5.
They have the same
booth every year.
A huge amount of excitement.
People love it.
A lot of people have ordered it.
They haven't figured
out how to build it.
The price has gone
up to the point where
you can almost by a Cessna
Caravan on floats with a jet
engine for the same price.
Here is a retired Air Force
and Southwest Airlines
pilot with his electric
self-launching Pipistrel
glider.
Pipistrel is the
company to watch.
They do a lot of
interesting stuff
in Slovenia, especially
with electrics.
This is not the kind
of radar picture
you want to see when
you're in a $99 tent.
I will say to Costco that it
did hold up remarkably well.
But it was scary.
The seaplane base a few
miles away from Oshkosh.
They have the Oshkosh
seaplane base.
I think it's on Lake Winnebago.
So you take a shuttle bus
or you drive over there
if you have a rental car.
So you'll see-- they call it
the quiet part of Oshkosh.
It's quiet because you only hear
about three or four aircraft
engines running at any
one time and maybe two
takeoffs or landings.
They have four hangars, vendors.
If you want to take your dog
in an unpressurized airplane up
to 18,000 feet, you
can buy this kit.
I don't know what our golden
retriever would say about that.
There's affinity groups
for different slices.
Here's a woman who just
like-- just for female pilots
to Mooneys.
Air shows every day.
My favorite acts actually were--
I did like the GameBird.
That was cool.
But I also liked
these first two were
kind of regular
family airplanes just
being pushed to their limits.
It wouldn't be legal just to
go out and do that in a Baron,
because you can't do acrobatics.
But he'll put it into
experimental category,
and then just fly it
right up to the G limits
for which it was designed.
And it's amazing to see
what these ordinary family
or business airplanes
can do when pushed.
There were-- one thing
that's interesting,
about 150 Beechcraft
aerobatic Bonanzas were built.
They were strengthened.
And it is legal to do aerobatics
in your four-seat Bonanza.
Night airshow.
I guess that's worth showing.
It is so unusual.
They had explosives and
fireworks mounted on aircraft.
They fly around at night,
shooting fireworks off.
I guess you may have to
view that on your own,
which isn't so bad.
A lot of warbirds.
Everything from
World War II is still
flying pretty much at Oshkosh.
That Grumman Tigercat
on the right,
I'd never even heard
of that airplane
until I saw it at Oshkosh.
That's-- I think this
is EAA's own B-17,
which they fly around and
sell rides in and stuff.
Oh, and up on the top right
is a flying 1/3 Scale B-17
that some crazy guy spent
15 years building or more.
That's EAA.
Also, they have a B-29.
Up there at the top right is my
friend Eric with his personal--
I guess he's in the foundation
with a few other people,
but essentially a personal DC-3.
Oh, and he's flying
that to Europe
this year for the 50th
Anniversary of D-day.
Is it the 50th?
No, it can't be.
AUDIENCE: 75th.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: What?
75th.
Sorry.
Thank you.
I was a math undergrad.
Good illustration of the
value of a Course 18 degree.
And actually, when
I was an undergrad,
people said, how
will you ever get
a job if you're a math major?
The engineers all said that.
Well, we said, well, we
can become actuaries.
We can become actuaries.
There was a group of folks who
were passionate about warbirds
down in the south.
And they called
their organization
the Confederate Air Force.
Well, they've had
to change that now.
Now they're the
Commemorative Air Force.
And they're big into--
they brought the
Tuskegee Airmen,
some of the remaining P-51
guys from World War II there.
I gave a talk with NOAA.
That's Kate from NOAA trying to
get volunteer pilots to fly sea
turtles back from Cape Cod
and other northern places
to Florida.
Sunday morning, it
was time to leave.
For me, I saw 30% of
what we'd hoped to see
and 1% of what there was to see.
As you can see from the
right, that One Week Wonder's
coming together.
It actually did fly,
I believe, on Sunday.
So they got it built
in seven or eight days.
We went to Mackinac
Island, beautiful place up
near the Canadian border.
Everything's horse-drawn
or a bicycle.
A fun place to go
in the airplane.
We went and landed in
the Toronto City Island
Airport, which is right
in front of the downtown.
We had Chinese food,
saw the aquarium,
landed back in Bedford.
So we burned off 15
hours of Hobbs time.
Split by three people, that
wouldn't be too horrible.
It was about $3,000 at retail.
Next year, I think it might
be time to go JetBlue.
So the summary is that
even as the regulation
has made light aircraft
almost as expensive to operate
commercially at least or for
charter as the big aircraft,
but Oshkosh keeps
growing every year.
More people are
passionate about it.
So what you're seeing
in the aircraft world
is like the very high
end and the very low end
are kind of prospering.
This is Oxana's thing.
She asked everybody like,
what brings you to Oshkosh?
And they always
said, the people,
I love talking to
the people here.
And I feel that way, too.
People go year after year.
There's a whole bunch of links
here in the presentation.
And finally, what I
like most about it is--
and the reason I'm going back,
I think, is it's my safe space.
Outside of this room
if I tell people
I like to go over
to Hanscom Field
and fly this little four-seat
airplane with a piston engine,
they're horrified.
They think that
that's just so dumb.
You could just drive in
New York in your Honda.
You could get a ticket
on JetBlue for no money.
Like why would you do that?
It's dumb.
But Oshkosh is the one place
where nobody will say that.